<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dsq="http://www.disqus.com/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.0/"><channel><item><title>We’re looking for donations</title><link>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/blog/255-we-re-looking-for-donations</link><content:encoded><![CDATA[Do we provide useful research or coaching? Support our service.

We’re looking for donations to develop 80,000 Hours.

We set up 80,000 Hours because we believe it is our best opportunity to make the most difference in the world. There’s an enormous opportunity to help thousands or even millions of people to find the opportunities that enable them to make the most difference.

We’re looking for £360,000 to develop our content over the next two years, test to see if it works, and, if it works, prepare to take it to scale. During that time, we also anticipate carrying out hundreds of in-depth consulting sessions with the most high potential, altruistic young people in the world, spinning off high impact projects and raising millions for charity.

If you would like to talk to someone about donating, please contact development AT 80000hours.org.

You can see more details on what we have done and our plans on our [evaluation pages](http://80000hours.org/blog/251-summary-of-our-six-month-evaluation).

If you would like to donate now, please go [here](http://home.centreforeffectivealtruism.org/donate/80k).



##What can your donations buy?

Over 80% of our budget is for our staff. So extra donations mainly allow us to maintain and grow the team. We think our team represents exceptional value. It’s made up of highly able, dedicated people, who care a great deal about the impact they have in the world, and so work for less than they could make even at other non-profits.

* An extra £100 allows us to talk to 5 people one-on-one about their plans.

* An extra £500 enables us to do a full [case study](http://80000hours.org/blog/232-we-re-changing-our-career-coaching).

* An extra £1,000 enables us to host a graduate volunteer to do a month of research, including all overhead. In this time they could do projects like creating a framework for comparing two important options, such as research and earning to give, they could interview experts about promising talent gaps, or they could survey empirical data on important questions, like expected earnings estimates.

* An extra £25,000 enables us to hire an extra full time researcher or careers coach for a year, including all overhead. They could do something like deliver 50 in-depth case studies.

For more information on our budget, please see [our latest finance report](http://80000hours.org/blog/249-finance-report).


##What kind of return have you earned with donations in the past?

In only a year we have taken 80,000 Hours from a volunteer run student society to a professional organisation with 8 full-time staff that’s hosted within Oxford University offices.

Our key focus has been rapidly learning about what business model to pursue and what content to create. We think we have been successful in this aim, and have taken [our strategy through several major iterations](http://80000hours.org/blog/246-our-progress).

Despite not being our focus, we’ve had strong success in outreach. Web traffic took off after we started full time:

<a href='http://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eightythousand/posts/images/225/original/image_0.png?1379515036'><img alt="Image_0" class="image large" src="http://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eightythousand/posts/images/225/large/image_0.png?1379515036" /></a>

This led to growing membership about seven-fold from 120 in July 2012 to 1000 today.

<a href='http://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eightythousand/posts/images/224/original/1000.png?1379448824'><img alt="1000" class="image large" src="http://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eightythousand/posts/images/224/large/1000.png?1379448824" /></a>

In terms of charitable donations alone, we expect to have raised many times our costs on behalf of top charities. In addition we have:

*Received major media coverage*

We have been mentioned in The Washington Post, The New York Times, BBC Today Programme, The Daily Mail, CNBC, NPR, Quartz, and in Peter Singer's TED talk.

*Produced substantial content*

We’ve published over 100 blog posts, given one-on-one advice to over 100 people, and have published an article in a major philosophy journal.

*Contributed to creating a network of alumni and projects*

This period, Effective Animal Activism hired an Executive Director and was spun-off. We’ve begun talking to a group of top entrepreneurs about starting an incubator. We’ve seen several 80k alumni each donate over $80,000 in their first year alone, and enter jobs at Google, McKinsey, Jane St and Rothschild. 

*Completed key organisational set up*

We’ve grown from being a volunteer team to a professional organisation with 8 full-time staff and Oxford University offices in a just a year. We’ve also completed key legal set up.


For more on our cost-effectiveness, please see [our recent evaluation of 80,000 Hours as a project](http://80000hours.org/blog/248-evaluation-of-80-000-hours-as-project).


##Why do you think this project is high impact?

###The benefits

We’re the only people in the world who are systematically investigating the best opportunities for individuals to make a difference.

By preparing and delivering this information, we’ll have the potential to bring thousands of extra people to work on the most high priority opportunities in the world.

If our model works, it will be extremely cost-effective. 80,000 Hours will act as a multiplier on the resources going into whichever opportunity is best at the time. For instance, suppose we identify a promising idea for a new non-profit. We find someone better qualified than ourselves to take that position. Our team has less than 10 people, but we have the potential to help at least hundreds of other people enter the best opportunities.

An investment in us now enables us to transparently explore this possibility of having huge leverage to see if it really works. If it does, we’ll be able to massively scale it up, since the issue of which careers make the most difference is of interest to a large fraction of young graduates (for instance, see [this survey](http://80000hours.org/blog/108-net-impact-survey-hopeful-news-for-ethical-careers)) and no-one else is doing anything like this.

In addition, over the next two years, we anticipate the following extra benefits:
* Raise more than our costs in donations to top funding opportunities through promoting earning to give
* Do in-depth research to help the career decisions of at least 100 of the most altruistic, most high potential people we can find
* Prepare over a hundred research reports on which careers are best and how to choose them
* Build connections within the effective altruism community and promote the key ideas of effective altruism

For more detail on our plans, please see [here](http://80000hours.org/blog/250-team-plan)


###The evidence

In addition to the strength of the concept, we think the following strands support our case:

*(1) Success to date*

We have been successful in rapidly growing an effective, well managed organisation with a highly motivated team in very little time. 

We think this team has been successful in rapidly learning about which approaches work and adapting our strategy based on the evidence. In the last year, we have made four rounds of improvement to our strategy.

Further, we had significant outreach success, which gives us confidence that our model can work. For instance:
* We have been able to generate major press coverage for our ideas, including Peter Singer’s TED talk about effective altruism, Will MacAskill’s column on Qz.com and press coverage of [earning to give](80000hours.org/media).
* We have been able to significantly increase the the number of visits to our site, from about 2,500 unique visits per month in July 2012 to over 8,000 today.
* This has led to significant demand for our case studies. We now turn away over 90% of requests.
* We have had exponential membership growth to 1000 members, and over 10% of these say they anticipate significantly or completely changing their career because of 80,000 Hours.
* By working with people in-depth in the past, we have led to dramatic career changes. For more, see [our business plan](https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B-Jhoc5Aa_5WU09CcU1Sb254NlU/edit?usp=sharing). This includes several people choosing to pursue earning to give and donating tens of thousands of dollars to effective charities.
* We have already been able to help fill some high priority career opportunities by finding a trial hire for GiveWell, a staff member for Giving What We Can and a staff member for the Future of Humanity Institute.
* We have already spun-off an [entirely new charity operating in a high priority area](www.effectiveanimalactivism.org).


For more details on what we’ve achieved and what mistakes we have made, see our [evaluation](http://80000hours.org/blog/248-evaluation-of-80-000-hours-as-project).


*(2) The base rate*

We think we operate at the intersection of several broad promising areas, which increases our confidence about our impact to date and the promise of our model.

1. As we will argue in an upcoming post, we think cause prioritisation is a highly promising area. 80,000 Hours contributes directly to cause prioritisation by carrying out and collating career prioritisation research.

2. We’re part of the effective altruism movement, which is itself growing very rapidly and has produced highly cost-effective projects like GiveWell, which we aim to model ourselves on.

3. On average, it’s [easy](http://80000hours.org/blog/92-why-don-t-charities-spend-more-on-fundraising) to raise more than $1 for charity per $1 spent fundraising. An element of what we do is fundraising for effective charities. The rest of what we do is analogous to fundraising except it involves human capital.


*(3) The team*

You pay for a [highly able team](/meet-the-team) at a very low price. Our staff work for lower wages than they could receive elsewhere, even in the non-profit sector, because their core aim is making the most difference.


*(4) Our motivations*

We’re working on this project because we think it’s one of the best ways for us to make a difference in the world. We hold ourselves to high standards of evidence, and if we don’t think what we do works, we’ll either change it or scale back the project.


*(5) The market niche*
 
We think there’s a clear case of a market niche. There’s strong and growing demand for careers with a social impact among young people.[^1] But there’s little guidance as to what’s best. The few ethical careers services that exist (ethicalcareers.org; ethicaljobs.net; ethical-jobs.co.uk) are small and often superficial in their advice, lacking key considerations such as those listed [here](http://80000hours.org/our-features). Moreover, people are dissatisfied with careers advice in general: our survey found that only 15% of students in Oxford find existing careers services “very useful” and we’ve been able to generate substantial interest in our alternative careers service in little time.


##What are you plans and strategy for the future?

Please see [our business plan](https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B-Jhoc5Aa_5WU09CcU1Sb254NlU/edit?usp=sharing) and [our latest six month review](http://80000hours.org/blog/251-summary-of-our-six-month-evaluation).


##How can I get more information and donate?

If you would like to donate now, you can [use paypal or arrange a bank transfer](http://home.centreforeffectivealtruism.org/donate/80k)

If you have more questions, you may find the answer in [our latest six month review](http://80000hours.org/blog/251-summary-of-our-six-month-evaluation), otherwise please contact development AT 80000hours.org. You can also contact this address to receive a pack of further materials.

* * *

*Notes and References*

[1]: Over 70% regard ethical considerations “crucial” in their choice of employer (the Guardian) over 80% of Oxford students want to make a positive impact (our survey), and [31% of American students say making an impact is “essential.”](http://80000hours.org/blog/108-net-impact-survey-hopeful-news-for-ethical-careers)

[2]: Our survey of 120 students in Oxford.]]></content:encoded><dsq:thread_identifier>ÿ</dsq:thread_identifier><wp:post_date_gmt>2013-09-15 23:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt><wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status></item><item><title>The worst ethical careers advice in the world</title><link>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/blog/183-the-worst-ethical-careers-advice-in-the-world</link><content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href='http://s3.amazonaws.com/eightythousand.org/posts/images/153/original/apple_pink_logo_with_words.png?1369646066'><img alt="Apple_pink_logo_with_words" class="image large" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/eightythousand.org/posts/images/153/large/apple_pink_logo_with_words.png?1369646066" /></a>

What are you going to do with your life?

If you’re like most young people, you care about making a difference. But who’s there to help you with that? So much of the career advice out there today is unhelpful cliches. Here’s some of the most common career advice we’ve found over the last six months that you shouldn’t follow.


1\. **Do what you’re passionate about**

Perhaps the most common advice of all. It’s espoused by hundreds of advice gurus and public figures, perhaps most famously Steve Jobs, who told the Stanford class of ‘05 *”you’ve got to find what you love”*, in a [video](http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UF8uR6Z6KLc) that has gone on to have over 16 million views.

But when Jobs was young, his passions were history, dance and eastern mysticism. Is that what he should have done? He first got into computers as a way to earn cash on the side.

This advice gets things backwards, since passion develops out of applying yourself to something worthwhile. It’s not helpful to think that your passion is out there, waiting to be discovered. You create your passion.

We’ve already offered a comprehensive take-down [here](http://80000hours.org/blog/62-don-t-do-what-you-re-passionate-about-part-1).


2\. **Do what you’re good at**

Better, but consider, I’m amazingly good at meat packing. Is that what I should do? This advice is incomplete at best. 

And similar to ‘do what you’re passionate about’, it gets things backwards. Getting good at something is the result of thousands of hours of practice. So, your choice of career is *more* a choice of ‘what should I get good at?’ rather than ‘what am I already good at?’


In part, these two slogans go wrong because they’re too inwards facing - they don’t consider *what the world needs*, even though this is clearly important in itself, *and* working on something valuable is the key to a meaningful career.

But people who want to focus on *contributing* face another slew of bad advice. For instance:


3\. **Work in a non-profit**

People interested in leading a career that makes the world a better place are often encouraged into the non-profit sector (or else the public sector). This is evident in the UK in the ‘ethical careers’ movement, led by books like *The Ethical Careers Guide*, which prominently features a variety of non-profit jobs as ‘ethical careers.’

Working at a non-profit can be a great way to make a difference. But it’s no guarantee. Amazingly, lots of non-profits probably have [**no**](http://80000hours.org/blog/66-social-interventions-gone-wrong) [**impact**](http://80000hours.org/blog/100-let-s-stop-building-schools). And do workers at non-profit have more impact than [the people](/earning-to-give) who fund them? The researchers who push forward progress? The entrepreneurs who transform the economy? Policy makers? Maybe. No one stops to ask.

Further, even if the non-profit itself has an impact, if it has a lot of people who want to work for it, then your individual contribution might be relatively small. You’ll just be taking the job from [someone else]((http://80000hours.org/blog/35-the-replaceability-effect-working-in-unethical-industries-part-1).


4\. **Avoid ‘bad’ industries**

As well as being encouraged into the non-profit sector, one is pushed away from the ‘bad’ industries. Don’t work in finance, law or advertising. 

But this is clearly an oversimplified message. Not every job in finance is obviously bad. And there’s a difference between the harm done by an industry and the harm done by an individual working in the [industry](http://80000hours.org/blog/35-the-replaceability-effect-working-in-unethical-industries-part-1). Moreover, this advice ignores the potential one has to use these positions for good, either by receiving valuable training, an influential network or lots of money that can be used to fund good causes.

Perversely, since this advice is widely believed, bad industries can offer *more* opportunities for having a real impact. If people with good motivations become less inclined to take these positions, then you’d expect there to be more un-taken opportunities left lying around to make a difference. This is certainly the case with donating money, with the rich donating a [*smaller*](http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2013/04/why-the-rich-dont-give/309254/) fraction of their income to charity than the average.


5\. **Follow your values**

Better again. But it’s still just the beginning. This advice is frequently offered, and has some alternative forms like ‘follow your heart’ or ‘do what’s right.’ But it’s normally offered without an appreciation of how hard it actually is to work out your values in the first place, or any of the information you’d need to do so. After all, there’s an entire academic discipline dedicated to the study of creating a good value system (ethics), which doesn’t offer many easy answers.

As an example, consider the following advice: “Write out a list of organisations you feel do good. Try to briefly define what good was done. What themes emerge?” Suppose what comes to mind are a bunch of organisations that plant trees to reduce climate change. Is ‘helping the environment by planting foliage’ what I ultimately value and should devote my career to? Frequently, this is as far as we go. But if you really think about it, there will be other things you care about. For instance, if you could cover part of Africa in forest at the cost of causing a huge famine, would you do it? 

In reality, there are many tough trade-offs to make. Donating $2000 to a charity planting trees, means an [extra person](http://www.givewell.org/international/top-charities/AMF#Costperlifesaved) dies of malaria. Brushing the trade-offs aside is not acceptable.

* * *

Finding advice like this is our motivation for setting up 80,000 Hours. We want to develop the best advice out there on how to make an impact with your career.

Over the next six months, we’ll be publishing a complete package of material on our site to get you started on leading a high impact career, which we hope will start to overcome these cliches.

But before that, we want to know exactly what your sticking points are. What’s the worst advice you’ve received? What have you tried and failed? If you could change one thing about your career, what would it be?

I’d love to hear your thoughts in our short five question survey [here](https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XyMrI_re14xqjqyNL_jAcEMO8c0IcqMaiWUeRl7dOU4/viewform). 

Or send me an email at ben at 80000hours.org. I read every one.

***

[SURVEY: What's the worst careers advice you've received?](https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XyMrI_re14xqjqyNL_jAcEMO8c0IcqMaiWUeRl7dOU4/viewform) ]]></content:encoded><dsq:thread_identifier>·</dsq:thread_identifier><wp:post_date_gmt>2013-05-25 15:43:00</wp:post_date_gmt><wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status></item><item><title>Summary of our six month evaluation</title><link>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/blog/251-summary-of-our-six-month-evaluation</link><content:encoded><![CDATA[*This is the final post (of a series of six) on our six month evaluation*

This report overviews our entire six month evaluation. Our Six Month Review is divided into 9 sections. Click on the links to see the full reports.

You can see a commentary on this review by the trustees and external advisory board of 80,000 Hours [here](http://80000hours.org/blog/252-trustee-and-advisory-board-re).

 

[(1) Our Progress](http://80000hours.org/blog/246-our-progress-dec-2012-may-2013)

Highlights our main achievements and mistakes in the period.

* Our key priority was further developing our business model and content plans, and we’re pleased with our success in this area. We made two rounds of improvements, culminating with adopting the ‘[case study model](http://80000hours.org/blog/232-we-re-changing-our-career-coaching)’ - we outline our key ideas then do further research by doing in-depth consultations on the career decisions of high potential people.

* Our next major priority was further building 80,000 Hours and the Centre for Effective Altruism as robust, effective organisations. We made mistakes in this area, but overall I think we made strong progress. We successfully coped with almost a doubling of the number of people working at the Centre for Effective Altruism.

* While prioritising developing our business model and organisation building, we’ve also performed strongly in outreach and content. Increasing web traffic by 47% and recruiting about 400 new members was well ahead of expectations.

* We made many mistakes this period, but I’d classify most as minor mistakes or just ways things could have gone better. The worst mistake was that the operations team ran out of capacity in March, slowing down our overall progress.

[(2) Metrics Report](http://80000hours.org/blog/247-metrics-report)

Highlights our key outreach and membership metrics.

[(3) Evaluation of 80,000 Hours as Project](http://80000hours.org/blog/248-evaluation-of-80-000-hours-as-project)

Answers a set of crucial questions for stakeholders of 80,000 Hours.

* We believe it’s likely but highly uncertain that our current business model and content is effective relative to GiveWell’s top recommendations, and we continue to rapidly improve our business model.

* We continue to learn about how to function effectively as an organisation (as explained in [Our Progress](http://drive.google.com/open?id=1piKbNzsRK3ZY19fKtbGma4cHzCR_Bjpg-W8UDCNtSm8)). One significant challenge ahead is learning how to effectively run a larger, three tier organisation.

* We continue to rely heavily on our key staff, though we’re making progress towards reducing this reliance.

* We’re not financially weak, but there is significant room to become more secure.

* Our team is highly able and reports high levels of satisfaction, and we’re attracting very talented applicants, especially to our internships. Nevertheless, we are being somewhat slowed down by not being able to find enough talented staff.

[(4) Trustee Performance Evaluation of 80,000 Hours](https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B8OdBVMpAjJHQWJEZC1QeFhIYnc/edit)

Evaluates the effectiveness of our model to date.

[(5) Our Plans for the Next Six Months](http://80000hours.org/blog/250-team-plan)

* We continue to see the top priority as further investment i.e. developing our business model, content and the organisation’s robustness.

* The flagship goal in this area is carrying out 30 case studies, which will form the centre of our content and evaluation efforts.

* Also important is: (i) more impact evaluation in general (ii) fundraising enough to keep up with our expanding budget (iii) increasing our talent pool through training and outreach (iv) increase the appeal of our content to successful young professionals through rebranding (v) having high quality research on our key ideas to support the case studies.

* Outreach is less high priority, except insofar as we do enough to ensure a strong stream of candidates for case studies and internships, and build up credibility (e.g. receiving press coverage, impressive affiliations).

* We’re also not yet focused on scaling up delivery, because we think it will be overall faster to spend more time developing our content at this stage.

[(6) Finance Report](http://80000hours.org/blog/249-finance-report)

* We spent £79,000 last year, which paid for about 2.7 full-time staff and 4.7 full-time interns.

* 85% of our budget was spent on staff salaries and intern expenses. The majority of the remainder is spent on office costs.

* Our central projection is to spend £160,000 over the following year

* We have £30,000 of cash on hand, which is two months of reserves. Our target is to have at least six months of reserves.

* Our room for funding over the next 12 months is at least £360,000.

[(7) Our Latest Business Strategy](https://docs.google.com/document/d/1OFOtzhrTHfw7CkDjDEQ7l4JQrw02hZrESauGV10xCgs/edit)

Gives an overview of our current programs, impact model, impact tracking approach, funding model and 2-5 year expansion plans.

* Our ultimate aim is to do the most good by promoting the community that supports effective altruism.

* The key problem we address is: People don’t have enough access to high quality information on how to make a difference with their productive time.

* Our Vision: The most high potential people in the world are taking the most high impact opportunities to make a difference.

* Our Mission: Move the most high potential people into the world’s most pressing talent gaps.

[(9) Our Latest Summary Business Plan](https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B-Jhoc5Aa_5WU09CcU1Sb254NlU/edit?usp=sharing)

Presents a summary of the investment case for 80,000 Hours.

[(9) Our Team](http://80000hours.org/meet-the-team)]]></content:encoded><dsq:thread_identifier>û</dsq:thread_identifier><wp:post_date_gmt>2013-09-05 00:09:00</wp:post_date_gmt><wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status></item><item><title> Case Study: Designing a new organisation that might be more effective than GiveWell's top recommendation</title><link>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/blog/254-case-study-designing-a-new-organisation-that-might-be-more-effective-than-givewell-s-top-recommendation</link><content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href='http://s3.amazonaws.com/eightythousand.org/posts/images/102/original/fundraising.png?1362203542'><img alt="Fundraising_for_effective_altruists" class="image large" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/eightythousand.org/posts/images/102/large/fundraising.png?1362203542" /></a>

##Introduction

Several months ago, we [wrote about](http://80000hours.org/blog/162-how-to-create-the-world-s-most-effective-charity) an apparently easy way to create a charity that’s more effective than [GiveWell’s](www.givewell.org) top recommendations. It’s a simple idea: create an organisation that does nothing except  fundraise for GiveWell’s top recommendations. It [seems relatively easy](http://80000hours.org/blog/92-why-don-t-charities-spend-more-on-fundraising) to raise more than $1 for every $1 invested in fundraising, so it seems relatively easy to act as a multiplier on donations to other charities, and thus create an organisation with a cost-effectiveness ratio that’s higher than the charities themselves. 

The idea has merit from other angles too, for instance, [there’s reason to expect](http://80000hours.org/blog/92-why-don-t-charities-spend-more-on-fundraising) that charities don’t fundraise as much as would be optimal, and it’s a valuable service to them to take fundraising off their books. It’s also promising because the success of fundraising is relatively easy to quantify compared to many other meta-charity activities (like doing research or advocacy). This means that you can learn quickly whether you’re succeeding, which means you can improve quickly.

We were thrilled, therefore, to find that two 80k members, Joey and Xio, are planning to start an organisation that does exactly this. It’s called [Effective Fundraising](http://www.effectivefundraising.net/). Their plan is to start by writing grants for [Against Malaria Foundation](http://www.againstmalaria.com/) (AMF) and [The Humane League](http://www.thehumaneleague.com/) for six months. If it goes well, they could hire more people. Longer term, they could expand into others kinds of fundraising. They chose grant writing because (i) surveys of average fundraising ratios found that grant writing earns an average return of around $8 for every $1 invested, which is higher than most other forms of fundraising (ii) the money can be raised within 6-18 months, unlike ‘chugging’ (asking for donations on the street) or door-to-door which takes several years to pay off.

Joey and Xio sought out a huge amount of advice on their strategy. They’re some of the most altruistic people we know, and recently put college on hold in Canada in order to work on effective altruist start-ups. One of the sources they consulted was 80,000 Hours, and we were very happy to help. Rob Wiblin and I spent several hours thinking about their strategy and several hours discussing with Joey and Xio. (They have also sought advice from the other employees of 80,000 Hours and our President, Will MacAskill).

Joey and Xio were mainly seeking advice on how best to execute the project. In the rest of this post, we outline the main recommendations we made during the course of the discussion. Although our discussions didn’t lead to an immediate change in their plans, we hope this contributes to the discussion that Joey and Xio have been leading on how best to fundraise for top GiveWell recommendations, and inspires others to consider similar ways to make a difference. In summary:

## Summary

We think:

1. Working on Effective Fundraising looks like a very strong option for building career capital.
2. They could consider running more experiments before committing to grant-writing for 6 months.
3. They may be having less impact than they could because they may not be supporting the most high priority causes.
4. They should strongly consider hiring someone else to work for Effective Fundraising as a grant writer.


### (1) We agree that working on Effective Fundraising looks like a very strong option for building career capital

By founding their own organisation, we expect them to learn a variety of very useful entrepreneurial skills very rapidly. They should also improve their ability to fundraise, which is a highly useful skill for someone looking to work in the non-profit sector, but also involves sales skills that are useful almost everywhere.

This seems better than the skill development they could have working at another effective altruist organisation, where they would probably be given less responsibility, particularly if they make sure they prioritise learning while running Effective Fundraising (which they are).

In addition, Effective Fundraising offers more long-term upside. If it works, it could grow into large, new organisation within effective altruism.


### (2) They could consider running more experiments before committing to grant-writing for 6 months.

We both agree that it’s very important to test this project before scaling it up. We place higher weight on this factor than Joey and Xio, because because we think:
1. There’s a large amount of uncertainty about much money they might expect to raise with different methods
2. It seems relatively easy to learn more about how much money they might expect to raise by trying out different methods for a couple of months each.
3. This information would be very valuable, because it could significantly improve how they spend a year of effort, and the information would be valuable to other effective altruists considering the same thing.

Moreover, we think testing grant writing has lower value of information than testing other fundraising, because the feedback is weak. 

First, grant writing often has low success ratios. If your base rate of success is only 5%, then you will need to write a lot of grants to measure your ratio. We did a quick analysis, assuming that you have a 50% chance of being as good as professional grant writers (who we modelled as having three levels of ability, based on [Institute of Fundraising](http://www.institute-of-fundraising.org.uk/research/fundratios/) (IoF) data and assuming a base rate of success of 5%), and a 50% chance of not being able to raise money via grant-writing. We then asked: how many attempts would you have to make before you can be confident that grant writing is better than a guaranteed 3 times pay-off? Assuming a binomial distribution on successes, and performing a bayesian update, we found:
* It would take 47 failures in a row to become 90% confident that grant writing is worse
* It would take 13 failures in a row for the expected value of grant writing to drop below a guaranteed 3 times return.
* On the other hand, 2-3 successes out of the first 5 or so would push grant writing strongly ahead.
(You can see the spreadsheet [here](https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AuJhoc5Aa_5WdGF2TEpNSVJacFJZeTQ1TkktMGhKSUE#gid=7))

Second, you have to wait 6-12 months to hear the results.

Note that both of these concerns can be mitigated to some extent by starting with easy grants that have close deadlines.

Joey and Xio, however, think that the reasons behind grant writing are sufficiently strong that they should start immediately and do it for six months as a test. In particular they respond:

* The uncertainty is less than made out, because there is some data provided by the IoF on the returns of different methods. In particular, the average grant-writer makes 8 times their salary, and the bottom 15% make 5 times their salary. So, even if they perform at the bottom of grant writers, it will be better to do grant-writing than most other forms of fundraising.
* It’s harder to experiment than it looks. “You need licenses to do door-to-door fundraising and street fundraising, and it takes years for you to determine if the recurring donations have a good ratio. Legacies take several years, and sometimes decades to see returns. Both corporate and high net worth donors take considerable time to learn the field and become good at. In 6 months it might be possible to sufficiently test one of these. We think the data, while not as strong as we would like, is enough to show that grant writing is promising, and that it is worth a six to twelve month test.”

We note some countervailing considerations:
* It’s unclear how good the Institute of Fundraising data is, because they don’t publish their methods. For instance, they may not correct for survivorship bias - maybe fundraisers who don’t succeed don’t survive till the end of the year, so don’t appear in the data as collected. We’d also expect the figures to be systematically overstated, because charities have an incentive to keep fundraising costs low, so will try to put fundraising costs under different budget lines (moreover, this seems easier to do with grant writing or high net-worth fundraising than with chugging, because much grant writing is done by managers who have other responsibilities).
* The IoF data seems to be *the returns earned by people who currently work as grant-writers.* Grant-writers who earn less than 5 times their salary lose their jobs very quickly, so the data *obviously* shows that the ratios are higher than 5 times. This information doesn’t tell us much about how much money Joey and Xio might expect to earn by grant-writing.
* There are reasons to expect Joey and Xio will earn less. The average grant-writer is paid over £30,000 per year, which is a professional salary and probably equivalent to something like earning £60,000 in the corporate sector. This suggests that it’s a competitive field. On the other hand, this might be balanced out by the fact that (i) Against Malaria Foundation should be relatively easy to fundraise for (ii) Joey and Xio will prioritise learning and feedback so that they improve at grant writing as quickly as possible.
* Even if the licenses for other types of fundraising take several days of full-time work to get, it will still be worth it. Moreover, there seem to be ways to do tests without a license, for instance, you don’t collect payment details and instead just collect pledges for donations and email addresses.

In the end, we didn’t reach agreement. Joey and Xio still intend to commit to grant writing, while we suspect it may be better to prioritise experimentation slightly higher.


### (3) They may be having less impact than they could because they may not be supporting the most high priority causes.

We agree that supporting GiveWell recommendations is highly valuable and that the project has an attractive flexibility, since (to some extent) it will be possible to fundraise for different organisations as the evidence changes.

We think, however, that AMF and The Humane League might not be the most promising uses of money currently available, so Joey and Xio might be able to increase expected returns by funding someone else.

Joey and Xio’s response is that: They are a fundraising organization, not a charity evaluation organization. They take top recommendations from Givewell and Effective Animal Activism, two of the most recognized charity evaluators in their respective fields.

We think that going with GiveWell’s recommendations is a reasonable move as it’s plausibly the best charity evaluator in the world, but we also think it’s worth putting more effort into the decision if your aim is really to maximise expected returns. 

First, many leading experts both within and outside of effective altruism don’t think that GiveWell’s recommendations clearly offer the best returns. As three examples within global poverty, IPA, AidGrade and Giving What We Can are experts on evidence-based aid, and they don’t fully agree with GiveWell although there is overlap (see [here](http://www.poverty-action.org/provenimpact/testedandproven), [here](http://www.aidgrade.org/uncategorized/some-friendly-concerns-with-givewell) and [here](http://givingwhatwecan.org/where-to-give/recommended-charities)). Disagreements are even larger if you also consider charities outside the global poverty cause.


More importantly, *even GiveWell* [don’t claim](http://www.givewell.org/criteria) that giving to AMF is generically the use of money with the highest expected return. Rather they claim that it’s the best donation opportunity to an existing organisation that’s proven, scalable, has room for more funding and is transparent enough that uninvolved third parties can see that it is. This leaves open the possibility that there are organisations that might be more effective to fund, work for or set up:
1. Unproven organisations - these could worth investing in (a) to gain information about what works or (b) because they offer high expected return despite low certainty.
2. Organisations that Joey and Xio have special insight into not available to GiveWell.
3. Organisations that Joey and Xio could support to gain valuable information about what works that wouldn’t give GiveWell the same level of information.
4. Small organisations (if room for more funding is less than several hundred thousand dollars, GiveWell won’t normally investigate them, though [there are reasons](http://blog.givewell.org/2013/04/18/challenges-of-passive-funding/) to think many of these opportunities are taken, at least outside of meta-charity style projects).
5. Organisations that don’t exist yet, but could be created if a donor expressed interest in them or a credible entrepreneur started them. GiveWell has suggested that the approach of strategically picking a cause and then being an [active donor](http://blog.givewell.org/2013/04/18/challenges-of-passive-funding/) could yield better results, at least in some cases.
6. Organisations that GiveWell hasn’t had time to investigate yet.
7. Organisations that don’t share GiveWell’s values (e.g. GiveWell doesn’t currently factor animal welfare into their evaluation).
Going with GiveWell recommendations means ignoring opportunities to support organisations that fall into these categories, which plausibly contain organisations that are higher impact.

*Note that after this post was written, Holden replied (see the comments below), stating that GiveWell does believe that giving to AMF is currently the charitable donation opportunity with the highest expected return, in contraction to the statement above*

One response could be that making calls like this is difficult, so it’s better just to stick with GiveWell. But Joey and Xio have already decided to funnel 50% of the funds raised to Effective Animal Activism’s top recommendation, which has to date invested far less research time than GiveWell in charity evaluation. It seems inconsistent to overrule GiveWell in this case but not in the other cases.

As an aside, note that if you think that the best opportunities will typically be in these categories, then the idea of Effective Fundraising is slightly less attractive, because opportunities like these are typically difficult to fundraise for as an outsider (and seem easier to support through direct work or earning to give). We think it’s plausible that the best opportunities in these categories will often be more attractive than proven, scalable charities, because (i) value of information is very important because we’re highly uncertain what’s best and opportunities like this offer more information about what works (ii) being an [active donor](http://blog.givewell.org/2013/04/18/challenges-of-passive-funding/) or entrepreneur opens up the space of projects a great deal, which increases the chance finding a good one provided you have a search strategy that’s somewhat effective (iii) [broad market efficiency](http://blog.givewell.org/2013/05/02/broad-market-efficiency/) - if it has already been recognized by GiveWell, then it willl be attracting the attention of some major funders.


### (4)  They should strongly consider hiring someone else to work for Effective Fundraising as a grant writer.

Employing someone to write grants for AMF seems like a good use of money, but it’s something that you don’t need an effective altruist to do. Rather, it might be better to find a grant writer with a track record of several years and ask them to write the grants. This seems more proven and likely to result in higher returns more quickly. The fundraiser could also be paid partially on commission, reducing the downside to Effective Fundraising. This would free Joey and Xio up to work on projects that are less easy to outsource. Or, at least it could help them learn to grant write quicker. I offered to help them raise money to pay for such a person.

Joey and Xio raised some important additional points:
1. It would be difficult to raise the money, especially if they don’t want it to take funds away from effective charities.
2. It’s too risky - they prefer to trial the project themselves before scaling up.
3. They’re worried an external fundraiser might not be effectiveness oriented, which would make the organisation less flexible.
4. They did not feel an external fundraiser, costing three times their combined salary, would likely raise 6 times more per hour than they would.

We agree (1) and (3) are concerns, though don’t seem to sink the idea. Rather, it would be better to make some tests to see if (1) and (3) are true.

(4) is not the relevant comparison. First, what matters is marginal effectiveness not average effectiveness. Even if the extra fundraiser has a lower fundraising ratio, it could still be worth hiring them because it increases the total impact. Second, the ratio of money raised to salary is not what’s relevant from the perspective of maximising impact. Joey and Xio are happy to work on impressively low salaries, which boosts the headline cost-effectiveness of Effective Fundraising, but their opportunity cost also matters. Joey and Xio may have a higher opportunity cost than a fundraiser, because they may have the option to work on another highly effective project.

(2) also doesn’t seem right. If Joey and Xio try to write grants for AMF and fail, then we haven’t learned that Effective Fundraising is a bad idea. Rather, we’ve just learned that Joey and Xio shouldn’t write grants. In this case, it seems like you’d still want to find someone else to try to write grants for AMF. If Joey and Xio try to write grants for AMF and succeed, then they’ll want to hire someone else to scale up. Either way, they’ll want to someone else to be employed as a grant writer, and delaying that process is just slowing down moving money to AMF. Moreover, it seems that it’s less risky to hire a professional with a track record than to do grant writing themselves.

We didn’t reach agreement and Joey and Xio intend to delay hiring another staff member for at least 6 months.


## Further reading

If you would like to get involved, [contact Joey and Xio](http://www.effectivefundraising.net/contact-us.html).

If you want to read more about Effective Fundraising, see [this discussion](http://lesswrong.com/r/all/lw/i2s/introducing_effective_fundraising_a_new_ea_org/).

You can also check out an interview between our trustee Nick Beckstead, Joey and a donor [here](http://www.scribd.com/fullscreen/162710548?access_key=key-11juxn1x43fl0i9sm1xp&allow_share=false&show_recommendations=false).


If you’re interested in doing something similar yourself, we’d be interested in [doing a case study on your choice](http://80000hours.org/get-coaching).










 

]]></content:encoded><dsq:thread_identifier>þ</dsq:thread_identifier><wp:post_date_gmt>2013-09-12 15:27:00</wp:post_date_gmt><wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Դ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Sam Hilton</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>weeatquince@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/sam-hilton</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2013-09-21 14:04:05</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Well this post sets a very interesting precedent for one effective altruist organisation publicly criticising (albeit constructively) another effective altruist organisation.
I wonder to the pros and cons of this . . . ]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ե</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Florent Berthet</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>florent.berthet@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/florent-berthet</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2013-09-21 15:58:40</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Good point, Sam. I don't think there are too much cons for this as long as the critics stay constructive and acknowledge the positive aspects as well, which was the case here. This article will be a nice one to refer to if an EA gets a little too harsh with its fellows.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ԡ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Alexander Berger</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>alexander@givewell.org</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2013-09-12 19:29:28</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I work for GiveWell, which is extensively discussed above, but this response represents my personal views.

"If Joey and Xio try to write grants for AMF and fail, then we haven’t learned that Effective Fundraising is a bad idea. Rather, we’ve just learned that Joey and Xio shouldn’t write grants. In this case, it seems like you’d still want to find someone else to try to write grants for AMF."

This doesn't seem right to me. If six months of full-time work by two effective altruists doesn't yield reasonable returns, I think that should cause a significant update in the direction of "Effective Fundraising is a bad idea." I think we disagree because your toy model with a base rate of 5% chance of success but heterogenous grant writing talent doesn't strike me as very realistic. My understanding of the charity sector is that "grant writing appears to be a cheap way to raise funds" because writing grants is easy relative to the magnitudes of money involved and doesn't matter much, not because marginal increases in grant writing capacity will lead to proportional increases in funding. My model of foundations is that actual grant applications are normally a formality that cement an already-planned grant, and that grant writing is mostly a tax on non-profits. However, I'm not highly confident in that model, and I could readily update if Effective Altruism succeeds in raising funds via their grant writing efforts, so I'm excited that they're trying.

If Effective Fundraising fails to raise a considerable amount of money, then I think it's a mistake to update more in favor of "Joey and Xio shouldn’t write grants" than in favor of "our model of how grant writing works is wrong," especially in light of the low quality of the evidence used to justify investment in grant writing and, IMO, the relatively limited evidence for important differences in grant-writer quality. A low base rate would be a problem, but in that case I'd like to see better evidence about why we should expect a base rate as low as 5%, which I don't see a citation for and strikes me as too low.

This could be interpreted as an argument against focusing on grant-writing so completely so early, but I do expect the base rate to be relatively low, so a 6 month period of focus on one approach does not strike me as unwarranted. The same kinds of uncertainty might well surround other fundraising techniques, so picking one to pilot for a several month period and then reassess strikes me as a good strategic choice.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ԣ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Holden Karnofsky</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>Holden@givewell.org</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2013-09-12 19:30:06</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Hi, I'd like to clarify that we believe our top charities are the best giving opportunities we know of - all things considered. If we knew of better giving opportunities, we would publish them.

It's true that we believe better giving opportunities probably <em>exist</em>, and we started <a href="http://www.givewell.org/givewell-labs">GiveWell Labs</a> in order to find them. But we expect this to be a long and difficult road. We believe that being an active donor, supporting small unproven organizations, etc. is a higher degree of difficulty than supporting proven organizations, so we think it's not good advice to suggest that a small number of people running a part-time project pursue this approach rather than taking our recommendations.

Of course, it's always possible that a given person has connections, context and knowledge that we don't that leads to being able to spot a particular superior giving opportunity. But given that we are a full-time, multiple-staff operation devoted to finding the best giving opportunities we can, and Effective Fundraising is a part-time operation with a different primary goal, we don't understand the argument that Effective Fundraising should be trying - in addition to its primary goal - to do a better job than we are at our primary goal.

On another note, some of Elie's thoughts on the basic approach are available https://docs.google.com/document/d/1XYtWXc5__oZyq-_H8QJbY4ShbV_Az4Azerb2yfC0od0/ in the transcript of a conversation he had with Rob Wiblin (linked from http://www.givingwhatwecan.org/blog/2013-07-30/givewell-interview-on-causes-outside-global-health-givewell-labs-and-fundraising)
]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ԣ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Owen Cotton-Barratt</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>scatha@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2013-09-12 19:45:37</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I somewhat agree with the idea that hiring someone would be worthwhile. There is a conflict here, though -- really you want to get a very good grant-writer, and they may not be the ones in search of jobs.

I actually think that it might be best to try to hire a top grant writer to consult for them for a relatively short period. They could get this person to read over draft grant proposals they've made and make comments. This would probably improve the quality of the grant proposal (and so increase likelihood of funding), but it would also help Xio and Joey to learn high quality grant writing faster. I think this latter effect could be more important than the former.

Furthermore, it would increase the confidence you'd get in a negative result if you knew that your proposals had been judged as good by a top professional.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ԥ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Evan Gaensbauer</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>egbauer92@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/evan-gaensbauer</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2013-09-13 06:30:05</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Especially in light of the responses made by Messrs. Berger and Karnofsky above, I don't understand why Messrs. Todd and Wiblin would suggest that Effective Fundraising consider fundraising for other causes, when other organizations of effective altruism scarcely know how to identify what those causes might be. Unless a strongly reasoned consensus of the other charity evaluators such as Giving What We Can that Mr. Todd has cited above recommend poverty-reduction charities other than AMF. Alternatively, they could fundraise for organizations trying to reduce catastrophic or existential risks, yet it seems to me that the effects of such organizations are too far from settled or uncontroversial to warrant them being the target of Effective Fundraising's initial efforts. Also, as an aside, my intuition is that fundraising for existential or catastrophic risk reduction would be so different than fundraising for conventional charitable causes that an entirely different approach to it ought to be considered.

I do agree with Messrs. Todd and Wiblin that Effective Fundraising should perhaps be more wary of raising so much in terms of funds for EAA's top recommended charities, and experiment with different methods of fundraising. However, I don't know what to suggest those methods should be. Anyway, it seems to me such a strategy follows the maxim of 'if you're going to fail, fail hard and fast', so that effective altruism as a movement can learn what will and will not work in terms of fundraising, and learn how realistic the possibility of massive payoff from fundraising is.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ԩ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Florent Berthet</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>florent.berthet@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/florent-berthet</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2013-09-13 17:06:17</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I agree with Evan.

As a french EA who is considering doing the same thing in my country, I need to know as soon as possible whether this strategy is effective and how to improve it. Information is extremely valuable at this point, and it would probably be better to try several fundraising paths right from the beginning.

That said, kuddos to Joey and Xio, it's a fantastic initiative.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ԫ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Joey Savoie</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>joey.savoie@80000hours.org</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/joey-savoie</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2013-09-15 19:39:25</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[We were given a limited word count to respond to this post so I will try to address some of the comments here.

On “6 month period of focus on one approach does not strike me as unwarranted”. We agree and have written a further post here on how long we think (in very rough approximations) it would take to experiment with different methods of fundraising. 
http://www.effectivefundraising.net/1/post/2013/09/why-did-we-choose-grant-writing.html
In summary we feel it would take around six months or more to test any one type of fundraising, and it seems like strong usable information would not be gathered from a 1 month short test. In general most fundraising takes time to get good at and works better if you put more time into it/researching it. We feel testing several methods would yield both weak and unreflective long term representations of all the types tested.

We would be open to more well researched and well grounded suggestions on how to test different types of fundraising faster as this interests us greatly.

On “hiring someone” we think this is the strongest above suggestion and did consider it. One factor that moved us strongly towards not hiring someone with experience (at this time) is the large amount of free help we have received from fundraisers and grant writers, including reading over draft grant proposals and making comments. It has improved the quality of the grants and It has helped us learn. We think this help has carried most if not all of the benefits I imagined would be gained by hiring someone (without tripling our operating costs) and are very happy to have this help.

On not supporting the most priority causes, it seem that  either 80,000 hours has more confidence in our ability to evaluate and choose charities then they do Givewell’s (which seems clearly false). Or they personally disagree with AMF being the highest value cause in which case I would love to see detailed evidence based discussions with an organization that works full time on this issue such as Givewell. ]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ԭ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Benjamin Todd</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>benjamin.john.todd@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/benjamin-todd</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2013-09-15 22:47:34</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[1) One potential confusion that might be being made in several of these posts is equating “finding the best (charity) donation opportunity” with “supporting the best cause.” Supporting causes is broader than giving money, because it also includes (for instance) what you do with your labor, which includes a much broader range of plausibly good options in potentially more high priority causes than global health e.g. with your labor you can start a new organisation, which you can’t do as a passive donor (we’ll be writing about which causes are most high priority in the future).

Whether it’s better for Joey and Xio to support something more uncertain in another cause is very uncertain, but I think the question could be worth more work. Cases do exist e.g. I think it’s better for me to work at 80k than to devote myself to getting money for AMF.

(note that you could argue EF’s main value is supporting the cause of effective altruism because it acts as a proof of concept for an effective altruist idea, but this is not the argument Joey and Xio seem to have taken)

A related issue is the value of money given to charity vs the value of time spent working on activities not designed to raise money. Holden said in an interview with us that: “My intuition is that a really high fraction of the good that you accomplish with your career is the actual work that you are doing. When I think about the good done by a software company, I first and foremost think about what software does for the world, not about how much one will make and can give to charity, although that’s important too.” http://80000hours.org/blog/172-interview-with-holden-karnofsky-co-founder-of-givewell

Joey and Xio will hopefully raise more money via fundraising than via earning to give, but if it’s unclear that money donated via earning to give is more important than the value of your direct work in a productive sector, then it seems like it’s also uncertain (though more likely) that the value of money fundraised is higher than the value of the direct work in a productive sector.

2) Restricting ourselves just to giving opportunities (rather than supporting causes in general), my main point was that Joey and Xio were being inconsistent by overruling GiveWell in the case of The Humane League but not for the other types of exception that seem about equally reasonable e.g. if you’re less sceptical than GiveWell you could go with Project Healthy Children instead of AMF.

3) Thanks Alexander - I don’t have a solid model of grant writing and those comments strike me as reasonable.

4) Holden, apologies for the confusion on that point. I’ve added a note to look at your comment in the body of the post.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment></item><item><title>The best career advice you’ll never hear in a graduation speech</title><link>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/blog/187-the-best-career-advice-you-ll-never-hear-in-a-graduation-speech</link><content:encoded><![CDATA[“Follow your passion” is the stupidest career advice I’ve ever heard. Why? Because my passion in life is for singing bad karaoke. My friend Dodgy Dave’s passion is for dealing crack cocaine. Some of my friends have many passions. Most of my friends have none.

“Do what you’re good at” is better, but still stupid. It gets things the wrong way around. For almost all activities, being “good at” something is the result of [thousands of hours of practice and learning](http://www.uvm.edu/~pdodds/files/papers/others/everything/ericsson2007a.pdf) (pdf). In choosing a career, you’re almost always making the decision about what to become good at, not the other way around.

How, then, should you find a job you’ll love?

<a href='http://s3.amazonaws.com/eightythousand.org/posts/images/146/original/soon-to-be-graduates.jpg?1368979540'><img alt="Soon-to-be-graduates" class="image medium" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/eightythousand.org/posts/images/146/medium/soon-to-be-graduates.jpg?1368979540" /></a>

Here’s my slogan: ”Do something valuable.”

Let the problems in the world dictate what you do, rather than forcing a preconceived checklist labeled “success,” to be your motivation. Do something that genuinely helps others and makes the world a better place in a major way. That’s the way to have a happy, fulfilled life.

When I tell people this, half think it’s crazy and half think it’s trivial. I think it’s neither. So here’s a three-part explanation.

First, here’s the intuition. Think about yourself at 85, sitting on your rocking chair, looking back on your life. You, Version 1, think: “I made a ton of cash, own three beach houses and a yacht. But what was the point of it all?” Compare with You, Version 2: “I made a lot of money. I also dewormed the entire childhood population of Burundi. But what was the point of it all?” We find it pretty easy to imagine You, Version 1; but the thought of You, Version 2 being dissatisfied is jarring. If you want lasting job satisfaction, you should do something you find meaningful. And the best way to do something you find meaningful is to do something that actually is meaningful.

Second, here’s the science:

**Acting altruistically makes you healthier and happier.** [This study found that people](http://eprints.lse.ac.uk/24592/) who volunteer for good causes report higher levels of happiness and health than those who don’t volunteer. The authors suggest that volunteering gives you a sense of perspective—so that when you judge how well your life is going, you’re aware of people who are less privileged than you as well as people who are better off than you.

**Giving money makes you happier.** [Another study](http://www.sciencemag.org/content/319/5870/1687.full.pdf?sid=2b76fa84-7821-4bee-b2b4-309fa899866a) gave participants $20: half were told to spend the sum on themselves; the other half were told to spend it on others. It was the charitable half that reported greater happiness after spending their windfall, even though participants believed that spending on themselves would make them happier. Similarly, in a representative study of American citizens, those who donated a greater proportion of their income were happier, as were workers who donated a larger proportion of their bonuses.

And [it’s been found](http://www.orbee.org/images/5cc-resource-files/1319789168_Hackman%20%26%20Oldham%20%281976%29.pdf) (pdf) that **one of the most important factors in job satisfaction is how much your work affects the well-being of others.** Feeling that you’re making a difference makes it easier to get into the state of flow, or complete immersion in an activity. And, the greater significance you attribute to your work, [the higher your job performance](http://esoltanieh.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/Edwin_Locke_Handbook_of_Principles_of_Organizational_Behavior_Indispensable_Knowledge_for_Evidence-Based_Management__2009.pdf#page=139) (pdf).

Finally, I can speak from personal experience. I used to work because I wanted to be The World’s Best Philosopher—something like Wittgenstein 2.0. Now I work because I want to help others. This has improved my life in many ways. I now have a deeper sense of meaning and completeness in my life. I know I’m living up to my own values, rather than following the crowd. And I feel a tremendous clarity and resolution of purpose. There’s no messing around trying to find the “true me”—it doesn’t exist. In contrast, the problems in the world are real, and concrete. So I never doubt my aims now: altruism is the one thing you can do that you know you won’t regret.

When it comes to self-interest, everyone is competing for the same things: money, fame, power, status. So if you want anything, you’ve got to fight everyone else for it. But when it comes to altruism, there’s no competition—everyone wants the same thing, namely to make people better off. So it’s much easier to be wildly successful as an altruist—you’ll find other people supporting you at every step.

So does that mean you should drop everything and work for Oxfam? As [I’ve previously argued](http://qz.com/57254/to-save-the-world-dont-get-a-job-at-a-charity-go-work-on-wall-street/): not necessarily! What it does mean is that you should [start finding out what’s valuable](http://www.givewell.org/), and get help working out the ways [in which your career can make](http://80000hours.org/career-resources) for a better world.

***
*You may also enjoy*

* [How to be a high impact volunteer](http://80000hours.org/blog/110-how-to-be-a-high-impact-volunteer)
* [The power of effective activism](http://80000hours.org/blog/135-the-power-of-effective-activism)
* [Two questions you won't want to ask yourself but should](http://80000hours.org/blog/154-two-questions-you-won-t-want-to-ask-yourself-but-should)]]></content:encoded><dsq:thread_identifier>»</dsq:thread_identifier><wp:post_date_gmt>2013-05-20 08:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt><wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status></item><item><title>Why attractive people are dangerous</title><link>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/blog/89-why-attractive-people-are-dangerous</link><content:encoded><![CDATA[####Doing harm when you think you’re doing good - part 1####
&nbsp;
<center><a href='http://s3.amazonaws.com/eightythousand.org/posts/images/24/original/Anne-Hathaway-Catwoman-Bike.jpg?1348445187'><img alt="Anne-hathaway-catwoman-bike" class="image large" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/eightythousand.org/posts/images/24/medium/Anne-Hathaway-Catwoman-Bike.jpg?1348445187" /></a></center>
&nbsp;

It’s a sad fact, but attractive people are more persuasive than the rest of us[^footnote1]. In elections, attractive candidates seem to receive far more votes[^footnote2]. Attractive people even get paid more for doing the same work[^footnote3]. This influence seems to be subconscious. We don’t think beauty affects these decisions, but it does.

One day, you magnificent beast, you interview for an important job at the World Bank. The other applicant just isn’t in your league, not that you’d notice that. You’re not shallow. Anyhow, you go on to get the job. You don’t know it, but it turns out that the other applicant was a bit more qualified than you, but your appearance swung it for you. Your looks, however, are irrelevant to your skill in the job (you’re allocating funds to development programs, not modelling on the catwalk).

Several years go by. You do a lot of good work, which helps millions of people. Everyone is pleased.

Should they be?

If you hadn’t interviewed, and gotten the job as a result of your stunning looks, then the other person would have got it instead. And they would have been slightly better at it than you. They would have done more research, allowing the World Bank’s money to be spent more effectively. In fact, if the funds you allocate affect millions of people, and you do it just a little worse, then your true impact might easily have been to harm thousands of people. Oops.

So, attractive people, be careful. If you’re going to risk getting a job, try to get one where your natural advantages make you better at it. Everyone else, be suspicious. Attractive people can be dangerous.




* * *

[^footnote1]: For instance, more attractive people are assigned more favorable personality traits. For a review of the evidence, see this meta-study: Eagly, Alice H.; Ashmore, Richard D.; Makhijani, Mona G.; Longo, Laura C. [“What is beautiful is good, but…: A meta-analytic review of research on the physical attractiveness stereotype.”](http://psycnet.apa.org/psycinfo/1991-33123-001)
Psychological Bulletin, Vol 110(1), Jul 1991, 109-128.


[^footnote2]: MG Efran, EWJ Patterson, *”The Politics of Appearance”*, Unpublished manuscript, University of Toronto, 1976.
In this study of Canadian federal elections, attractive candidates received more than two and half time as many votes as unattractive ones. 73% of voters completely denied that their decision had been influenced by attractiveness.

[^footnote3]: This seminal study found that attractive people (in the same types of jobs, and of similar age) are paid 12-14% more than unattractive co-workers.
Daniel S. Hamermesh, Jeff E. Biddle, [“Beauty and the Labor Market”](http://www.nber.org/papers/w4518)
American Economic Review, vol 84, Dec. 1994, pp 1174-1194]]></content:encoded><dsq:thread_identifier>Y</dsq:thread_identifier><wp:post_date_gmt>2012-09-25 18:10:00</wp:post_date_gmt><wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ȩ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Ruairí Donnelly</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>rd5683@hotmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/ruairi-donnelly</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-09-26 12:53:11</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Haha awesome!

I noticed a typo; "One day, you magnificent beast, you’re interview(ed?) for an important job at the World Bank. "]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ȩ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Niel Bowerman</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>niel.bowerman@80000hours.org</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-09-26 14:01:25</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Amazing!  I like the writing style too.  ]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ȫ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Niel Bowerman</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>niel.bowerman@80000hours.org</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-09-26 14:19:23</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[You assume here that attractiveness is "irrelevant to your skill in the job".  I don't think this is true.  Given that more attractive people are more persuasive, and make better first impressions, you would expect, ***all other things being equal***, the more attractive person to be better at a job like running the World Bank.  The job requires lots of negotiating with foreign Government officials and giving speeches, both of which would benefit from having an attractive person at the helm.  Of course this is premised on them being as good at the other candidate at allocating resources, and the other more intellectually challenging aspects of the job.  ]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ȭ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Benjamin Todd</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>benjamin.john.todd@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/benjamin-todd</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-09-26 14:36:09</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[It seems pretty likely that there will be some cases where attractiveness helps you in the interview, but doesn't help in the job (or at least doesn't help as much as it helps in the interview). It would be pretty lucky if interviewers (who aren't purposely selecting on the basis of attractiveness) happened to subconsciously apply exactly the right weighting to it.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ȭ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Lex</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>agdfoster@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/lex</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-09-26 17:21:59</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[so if I think investment banking is immorale... i should Definitley go into into? ;)]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>˰</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Michael Johnston</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>michaeljohnston0@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/michael-johnston</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-12-08 17:30:52</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Candidate selection for various jobs is rather difficult.  It's hard to say whether the interviewer could tell, in marginal cases, which candidate is best qualified.  A lot doesn't go on a resume.

Is it possible that, as a result of biases through the lives of attractive people, they have received more benefits than unattractive people?  If so, isn't attractiveness then a signal of all the favor the candidate has received throughout his/her life?  Just a thought.  Many recruiters are not better than a coin toss.

Anyone read anything that speaks to this?

Also, what about men/women?  I'm not so informed, but I believe things like pay gaps are about as serious or more so.  This one's also a lot easier for members to pin down, when considering our own careers (although a survey of friends as to my own attractiveness might yield interesting results, too, I suppose).]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment></item><item><title>Dead children currency</title><link>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/blog/51-dead-children-currency--51</link><content:encoded><![CDATA[I think dead children should be used as a unit of currency. I know this sounds controversial, but hear me out.

According to Population Services International, a respected charity research group, it costs [between $650 and $1000](http://www.givewell.org/international/charities/PSI) to save one child's life through charity. You've probably heard lower numbers like twenty cents somewhere. The lower numbers are wrong. Yes, maybe an anti-measles vaccine for a kid in Africa only costs twenty cents, and measles can be fatal. But there's a lot of overhead, and you have to immunize a lot of people before you get the one kid otherwise destined to die of measles. I find the $650-$1000 figure much more believable. Let's round it off to $800.

So one dead child = eight hundred dollars. If you spend eight hundred dollars on a laptop, that's one African kid who died because you didn't give it to charity. Distasteful but true. Now that we know that, we can get down to the details of designing the currency itself. It should be a big gold coin, with a picture of a smiling Burmese child on the front, and a tombstone on the back. The abbreviation can be DC.

Of course, most things won't cost a whole dead child, so we'll need smaller denominations. There are four dead puppies to the dead child, since [dogs cost a bit above $200 to keep alive in an animal shelter](http://www.helpsaveastray.com/?f). There are two [burnt rainforests](http://www.staro.org/index.php?id=faq039s) per puppy, and five infected wounds(1) per burnt rainforest. I'm sure we can find talented artists to design the coins for all of these.

Yes, you grudgingly admit, such a system is technically feasible, but why in blue blazes would we want to replace our reassuring green dollar bills graced with dignified ex-presidents with that?

I leave that question to an article I read on the BBC site today: [woman spends £250,000 on a luxury doghouse for her Great Danes complete with spa and plasma TV](http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/gloucestershire/7750192.stm).

This does sound sort of ridiculous, but clearly it is not ridiculous enough. After all, at least one person thought it would be a good idea. Clearly, saying "doghouse that costs 250,000 pounds" does not carry the appropriate punch of "do not buy this."

And that's why I recommend switching to a dead-child-based currency. "Doghouse that costs 250,000 pounds" might not carry the proper punch. "Doghouse that costs 500 dead children" does. Using dead children as a unit of currency carries a built-in awareness of [opportunity](http://www.overcomingbias.com/2008/11/positive-vs-opt.html) [costs](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opportunity_costs). Yes, you can buy that doghouse, if you really think it's more important than spending that same money to save five hundred Haitian kids' lives. Go on! Dogs watching plasma TV! That sounds adorable!

After reading an article about [Mormon tithing practices](http://www.exmormon.org/mormon/mormon403.htm), I am hopeful that the switch from dollars to DCs will destroy organized religion as well. It sounds plausible for a church to say it needs two million dollars to move to a larger building. It even sounds plausible when a pastor gets up there in front of his congregation and says that God really wants every family to just give whatever little bit they're able, so that they can all buy a better house of worship and praise God in a more fitting sanctuary. My old synagogue did this for years, and no one found anything wrong with it; my parents even donated quite a big chunk of money. If my rabbi'd had to say "We need twenty-five hundred dead children to move to a sweeter pad", the gig would have been up.

Not like I am any saint myself. The past two years, I've spent about two dead puppies on books from Amazon.com alone. I am probably going to spend very close to a whole dead child to fly home for my two week winter break, and I spent ten dead children on my trip around the world this summer. I spent four infected wounds on fantasy map-making software. But at least in the back of my mind I realize I'm doing it. Can the people who spend a dead kid plus a dead puppy on [the world's most expensive sundae](http://www.boingboing.net/2006/02/14/worlds-most-expensiv.html) say the same? What about [the Japanese guy spending 1050 dead kids on a mobile phone strap](http://www.luxist.com/2007/01/03/diamond-studded-mobile-phone-strap/)?

One of America's top pro-life groups, Focus on the Family, spends [two hundred thousand dead children a year](http://blog.christianitytoday.com/ctliveblog/archives/2008/11/focus_on_the_fa.html) pushing its message of conservatism and opposition to abortion. Take a second to fully appreciate the irony there.

I'm not saying these people don't have a right to spend their presumably hard-earned money on whatever they want. Of course they have that right. I am just saying that if we took the simple common sense step of changing our monetary denomination from dollars to dead children, maybe they'd want something different.

C'mon, I bet you an infected wound it'd work great. 

_Dead children currency originally appeared (unnamed) on [Scott Siskind's personal website](http://www.raikoth.net/)_.

(1) Original source link now broken, alas.]]></content:encoded><dsq:thread_identifier>3</dsq:thread_identifier><wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-26 12:32:15</wp:post_date_gmt><wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ž</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>melissa madere</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>melissammadere@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-06-27 14:49:07</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Scott, I have too many mothers on FB who have lost children to have this posted on my wall...one 37 year old who lost FIVE...and her child's photo popped up right under this link.  While your story may have merit, I'm not reading and I'm removing you from my "like"...  try being a bit more sensitive to DEAD CHILDREN  those words aren't too nice to read side-by-side and you may offend more people than you recruit.
]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ſ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Max Deacon</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>maxdeacon@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/max-deacon</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-06-27 16:10:01</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Wonderfully blunt.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ɓ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>gwern</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>gwern0@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-06-27 19:06:55</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Reality is offensive; opportunity costs even more so.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ƃ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>gwern</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>gwern0@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-06-27 19:11:17</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[> (1) Original source link now broken, alas.

http://web.archive.org/web/20080213045409/http://www.kenyaredcross.org/aboutdetail.php?subcat=27&sublev=43 ? Searching the page text in Google leads to http://www.kenyaredcross.org/index.php?option=com_content&task=view&id=81&Itemid=158&pid=153&gid=40]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ƃ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Eric Herboso</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>ericherboso@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/eric-herboso</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-06-27 21:58:18</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Bravo.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ƅ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Rossa O'Keeffe-O'Donovan</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>rossaokod@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/rossa-o-keeffe-o-donovan</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-06-27 22:56:14</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Melissa, I would encourage you to read the blog post. Whilst Scott's title is no doubt provocative, his argument is merely that we should be aware of the power we have to prevent mothers, just like those you know, from having their children die. Unfortunately, many people seem blissfully unaware of the opportunity cost of their expenditure and as a result around 50,000 children die each day from preventable diseases. It seems to me that Scott is simply pointing out how easily preventable many of those deaths are.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ɔ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Chris Smith</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>christopersmith@europemail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-06-28 21:28:49</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Two quick thoughts here, though I'm largely in sympathy with the broad thrust of your argument.

1) If abortion is the destruction/murder of children, which many pro-life campaigners think it is, then the sums SPUC and other groups spend lobbying against the practice may well turn out to be very cost effective (assuming it makes at least some impact), even on your own value system which accepts, as most do, that children being dead is a bad thing. FOTF spend a lot of money elsewhere - James Dobson's salary is absurd and they pump out of lot of homophobic bigotry, but I think good consequentialists could well sympathise with pro-life campaign groups.

2) The cost of preventing child death is not constant, and the relative costs of dead children, dead puppies, burnt rainforests and infected wounds are not fixed either. I know you're not really advocating dead children as a currency, but it wouldn't be workable as you've outlined it.  I'd just stick with one of them as a measure of wasted money. (I remember an MP in the UK describing the cost of the government rescue of Northern Rock as '900 Millenium Domes' - this certainly made the point well).]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ƈ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Jacob Trefethen</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>jt497@cam.ac.uk</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/jacob-trefethen</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-06-29 06:34:15</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Ah, but as the cost of preventing child death is driven up by effective donation (diminishing marginal returns and all that) the bundle of goods one could buy for 1 deadchild will become larger over time (or, equivalently, the same bundle of goods will cost fewer deadchilds). As we all know, deflationary currencies can have disastrous effects. Once the economies of the developed world have crumbled there will be no one left to donate and prevent!

(Good post.)]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ǌ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Masato Yamaguchi</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>buckmbs@hotmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-08-06 11:05:16</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[For reference, the original title of this post was "A modest proposal".]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>Ș</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Julia Wise</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>julia.d.wise@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/members/julia-wise</wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2012-09-17 18:15:16</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I wrote a response to Scott's proposal and the ways I do and don't use it:
http://www.givinggladly.com/2012/03/tradeoffs.html]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment></item><item><title>How important is fitting in at work?</title><link>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/blog/169-how-important-is-fitting-in-at-work</link><content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href='http://s3.amazonaws.com/eightythousand.org/posts/images/112/original/not_fitting_in.jpg?1364021402'><img alt="Not_fitting_in" class="image large" src="http://s3.amazonaws.com/eightythousand.org/posts/images/112/large/not_fitting_in.jpg?1364021402" /></a>

##Summary

For most people, having a career which is a good “fit” for their personality is extremely high priority. Unsurprisingly, the notion of “person-environment fit” is fundamental to most careers advice. The general idea is that a) people have different personalities and interests, b) different types of people are suited to different working environments and c) finding the right working environment for your personality and interests is crucial to finding a job you’ll enjoy and be successful in.

However, despite several decades of research, psychologists have failed to demonstrate that personality/interests fit with the workplace has any substantial effect on job satisfaction or job performance. This suggests the normal approach of first working out your interests and personality and then finding a job to match them might be wrong - it doesn’t seem to help you find a job you enjoy or are good at!

This is surprising: it seems intuitively obvious that your personality fit with your job is important. It might be that the effect is too complex to be picked up in the existing studies, and that improved survey design would uncover a stronger connection. **But we should also consider whether being a good personality fit with your work is less important than we first think.** We’ve found good evidence that other factors: doing engaging work, as we define [here](http://80000hours.org/blog/134-our-research-on-how-to-find-a-job-you-love), and good social support at work, are important for finding a satisfying job. We’ve also had independent reason to think that following your interests [isn’t a good way to find a good job.](http://80000hours.org/blog/63-don-t-do-what-you-re-passionate-about-part-2)


**Therefore we recommend:**
* **Don’t focus so much on ‘following your interests’ and finding a job that fits your personality and interests type**
* **Instead, focus more on finding good social support (opportunities to receive help in the workplace), [engaging work](http://80000hours.org/blog/68-how-to-find-a-job-you-ll-love) (work with good feedback, autonomy, well defined tasks and so on), developing mastery of that work, and [making a positive impact](http://80000hours.org/blog/75-should-we-sacrifice-doing-what-we-love-to-make-a-difference-part-1).**


* * *


##Holland Types

To evaluate whether person-environment fit matters in job satisfaction, we need some way to measure it. “Holland types”, a theory developed by psychologist John Holland, are currently the best developed scheme, and indeed are one of the most empirically tested areas of work psychology.

According to Holland’s theory, most people can be categorised by six types for the purpose of job matching:

**Realistic:** (“Doers”) Enjoys manipulation of objects, working with tools, machines, or animals. Sees oneself as practical and mechanical. 

**Investigative:** (“Thinkers”) Enjoys systematic and creative investigation of natural and cultural phenomena, analysing and solving problems. Sees oneself as precise, scientific and intellectual.

**Artistic:** (“Creators”) Enjoys working in unstructured situations using imagination and creativity. Sees oneself as expressive, original and independent.

**Social:** (“Helpers”) Enjoys helping, informing, and training others. Sees oneself as helpful, friendly and trustworthy.

**Enterprising:** (“Persuaders”) Enjoys leading and persuading others. Sees oneself as energetic, ambitious and sociable.

**Conventional:** (“Organizers”) Enjoys working with data, carrying out tasks in detail and following others’ instructions. Sees oneself as orderly and good at following a set plan.

Each type appears to be a combination of personality and interests, though this is controversial in the literature. [^5]

##Holland’s Theory of Career Choice

Using Holland codes to determine person-environment fit in a career is supported by the [Handbook for Career Advising](http://www.amazon.co.uk/Handbook-Career-Advising-Josseybass/dp/0470373687), where it’s claimed that doing so “provides a useful structure that organizes a tremendous amount of information that can be readily applied”, providing a “structure for students to understand themselves.” The Occupational Information Network ([ONET](http://www.onetonline.org/)) has also put a huge amount of effort into [using Holland types](http://www.onetonline.org/find/descriptor/browse/Interests/).

How are Holland types used in career choice? Most people are all six types in varying degrees, and your three most dominant types make up your “Holland Code.” There are well developed tests you can take to identify your Holland Code, like the [Self-Directed Search](http://www.self-directed-search.com/). There are various free tests too, although they’re likely to be less accurate. The idea is that once you have your “code”, you can search for jobs which best match that code.

The key conclusion drawn from all this is that people are more likely to be satisfied and successful in environments where the environment type matches their personality type.

##How useful is this approach?

What evidence is there that this approach is actually predictive of job success and satisfaction?

The literature on this is controversial. One meta-survey argues that the theory is invalid.[^1] First, it claims there are different ways to measure “degree of fit” between person and work environment, and these different ways turn out to give significantly different answers. This is a serious problem for the theory as it means your “fit” with a job based on personality type is ambiguous. Moreover, the survey finds no correlation between degree of fit and job satisfaction.

Two large meta-studies (involving ~9,000 people) looking at degree of fit and job satisfaction found slight correlation between the two, but still surprisingly weak: one found a correlation of 0.1 and another 0.2.[^2] This hardly indicates the theory is highly useful for job selection, since it means it only accounts for 1-4% of the variation in levels of job satisfaction.

Similarly, a large meta-study on job selection showed that interests, as measured with Holland types, are only very weakly predictive of job performance, with a correlation of 0.1.[^6]

This said, demonstrating this kind of validity is complex. There are many reasons why the correlations might be weak even if the theory were in fact predictive. For instance, there might be a third, moderator variable that affects the strength of the relationship between degree of fit and satisfaction that we’re missing[^3], or the measures being used might simply be unreliable. It seems we have good prior reason to think that people do care about “fitting in” at work, and that this is justified, so we’d need strong evidence to think fitting in really doesn’t matter.

Something else worth considering is that, if Holland’s theory is correct, we’d expect people to have already self-selected into jobs based on their types (at least to some extent.) This would mean that merely performing correlation studies will understate how predictive of satisfaction the personality types are.[^4] To avoid this, ideally we’d want to perform full longitudinal studies. We might also want to investigate the extent to which peoples’ existing job choices fit with what the theory would prescribe based on personality type. 

There’s also independent evidence that people seem to move towards jobs with a higher degree of fit when given a choice. Assuming that people are correctly optimising for job satisfaction, this suggests that “degree of fit” as defined by Holland types is relevant.

Another study argues that degree of fit is a sufficient but not necessary condition for job satisfaction. If your Holland type fits with your work environment, you’re likely to be satisfied, but it’s also possible to be satisfied even if you don’t “fit” in this sense.[^7]

Finally, psychologists are investigating other measures of person-environment fit, which may be more promising.

It seems surprising that none of this debate is acknowledged by the Handbook of Careers Advice, and that the majority of careers advisers aren’t aware that the actual case for using Holland types is so weak. In fact, the literature on job satisfaction suggests that [much stronger predictors of job satisfaction are characteristics of the job itself](http://80000hours.org/blog/68-how-to-find-a-job-you-ll-love], but careers advice seems to focus less on this. This might be partly because Holland types depend on the individual so allow advisers to provide more personalised advice, whereas job characteristics depend on the nature of the job itself.

##What can we conclude from all of this?

The evidence is pretty unclear on how useful matching based on Holland codes is for predicting job satisfaction. This means that, for now at least, it’s probably better to focus on other things besides “person-environment fit”, such as job characteristics and social support, where the evidence is stronger. However, it’s worth noting that:

1. Improved survey design might uncover a stronger relationship between Holland matching and job satisfaction
2. The evidence that Holland matching is *sufficient* for job satisfaction is stronger, suggesting you could view Holland matching as one path (among several) to finding a satisfying job.
3. Even if Holland matching isn’t predictive of job satisfaction, this doesn’t mean that person-environment fit isn’t important, as this is only one way to measure it. Although, given the effort put into developing Holland types, it’s not a promising sign for the importance of person-environment fit.

* * *

*You might also enjoy:*

* [All our advice to date on finding a job you’ll love](http://80000hours.org/blog/134-our-research-on-how-to-find-a-job-you-love)

* * *

*Notes and References:*


[^1]: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S000187919991727X

[^2]: http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-115567607.html

[^3]: There’s some evidence evidence that the extent to which you care about fitting in with the group is an important moderator (pretty obviously!).

[^4]: Further explanation of this point: Holland’s theory says that 1. People will look for work environments that fit their personality type and 2. People are more satisfied in careers where there is a high degree of fit. If 1. is true, assuming people have at least some implicit knowledge of their own skills and preferences, people will be fairly well matched to careers to start with. This means that if 2. is true, then differences in satisfaction in careers must be mostly explained by factors other than personality - external factors or more objective job characteristics, for example. This would result in a weak correlation between degree of fit and and job satisfaction, even if the former is predictive of the latter.

[^5]: http://news.uofthenet.info/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/Spokane_Holland_s_theory_of_personalities.pdf

[^6]: *The validity and utility of selection methods in personnel psychology: Practical and theoretical implications of 85 years of research findings.*
FL Schmidt, JE Hunter - 1998 - American Psychological Association
http://mavweb.mnsu.edu/howard/Schmidt%20and%20Hunter%201998%20Validity%20and%20Utility%20Psychological%20Bulletin.pdf

[^7]: Spokane, A. R., Fouad, N. A., & Swanson, J. E. (2001). *Culture-centered
career intervention. Paper presented at a symposium on career intervention* (S. Whiston, Chair). San Francisco: American Psychological Association.]]></content:encoded><dsq:thread_identifier>©</dsq:thread_identifier><wp:post_date_gmt>2013-04-24 05:22:00</wp:post_date_gmt><wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status><wp:comment><wp:comment_id>ϙ</wp:comment_id><wp:comment_author>Alex</wp:comment_author><wp:comment_author_email>alexander.white45@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email><wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url><wp:comment_author_IP>255.255.255.255</wp:comment_author_IP><wp:comment_date_gmt>2013-04-07 00:37:53</wp:comment_date_gmt><wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Great post. It's nice to know that how personality interacts with career choice is not well understood in general; I have been wondering about this for a while.]]></wp:comment_content><wp:comment_approved></wp:comment_approved><wp:comment_parent> </wp:comment_parent></wp:comment></item><item><title>The value of economics phds: A conversation with Robin Hanson</title><link>http://eighty-thousand-hours-new-dev.herokuapp.com/blog/257-the-value-of-economics-phds-a-conversation-with-robin-hanson</link><content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href='http://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eightythousand/posts/images/228/original/robinhanson1.jpg?1380927881'><img alt="Robinhanson1" class="image large" src="http://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eightythousand/posts/images/228/large/robinhanson1.jpg?1380927881" /></a>


## Participants

* Robin Hanson—Associate Professor, Department of Economics, George Mason University; Research Associate, Future of Humanity Institute at Oxford University

* Nick Beckstead—Research Fellow, Future of Humanity Institute at Oxford University; Board of Trustees, Centre for Effective Altruism

* Jess Whittlestone—Director of Communications, 80,000 Hours

## Summary

**Purpose of the call:** We organized this call to learn more about the value of getting a PhD in economics to help advise people considering that path, which we think is a potentially promising route in academia.

**Why this person:** We sought Robin’s thoughts because he is a like-minded economics professor with whom we already had a relationship.

We discussed what career options are available to people who get PhDs in economics, who is a good fit for a PhD in economics, and how to maximize one’s impact in economics. We did not discuss highly data-oriented questions, such as PhD acceptance rates, tenure rates, and portions of economics PhDs working in different areas.

An economics PhD is

1. generally necessary for becoming an economics professor 		

2. can be a promising route (among some other potentially promising routes) to finding work in think tanks, government agencies, international organizations such as the World Bank,	

3. can be helpful for getting a job in consulting. 	

Good indicators of fit for an economics PhD include aptitude for math, interest in economics, being open-minded about research topics, being able to work on challenging tasks with little direction from others, and being willing to put in a lot of hours. A firm grasp of basic economics concepts and theory, developed through years of practice, is very valuable for understanding how the social world works, which is helpful for evaluating causes and interventions.

# **Questions about career progression for economics PhDs**

## Apart from becoming economics professors, what do economics PhDs do?

An economics PhD can also be helpful for finding work in think tanks, government agencies, international NGOs (such as the World Bank), and consulting. In general, the primary reason to get a PhD in economics is to become an economics professor. However, if someone had a strong desire to work at, say, the World Bank, it could make sense to get a PhD in economics for that reason.

## How does getting an economics PhD compare with other options for getting these types of jobs?

Research jobs at think tanks generally require PhDs (such as political science, public policy, or sometimes sociology) or law degrees. Some people with appropriate technical degrees can find work at subject-relevant think tanks, though there is still a need to show the ability to write policy papers. For example, someone with a PhD in computer science might find work at a think tank working on technology/internet issues. In very rare cases, people can get research jobs at think tanks without professional degrees by proving their ability to write on relevant topics. Matt Yglesias getting a job at the Center for American Progress is one example.

To maximize influence on policy, there is a strong presumption in favor of working in fields and research areas within fields that are most prestigious. For people who are a good fit for economics, this often favors economics over other PhDs or law degrees. However, law can be a better fit in cases where legal issues are very important. Political science stands out if one wants to influence policy by helping people win elections.

## How competitive are the non-university jobs?

Professor jobs are generally more prestigious and harder to get than jobs at think tanks, which are generally more prestigious and harder to get than jobs at government agencies. It is generally easier to move from the more prestigious jobs to the less prestigious jobs.

## How do non-university jobs compare in terms of impact?

The impact you can have in university jobs tends to be more indirect and flexible, whereas impact in think tanks or government tends to be more direct and focused on specific issues. If you know which issues you want to work on and believe those issues stand out in terms of opportunities for impact, this can favor the non-university jobs.

# **Who is a good fit for an economics PhD?**

Good indicators of fit include aptitude for math, interest in economics, being open-minded about research topics, being able to work on challenging tasks with little direction from others, and being willing to put in a lot of hours. Strong past academic performance is not a very strong indicator of good fit because it may not translate in ability independently choose good research questions and make progress on them.

# **How to maximize impact within economics**

## Selecting a PhD program

Prospective PhD students often underemphasize general prestige of a program relative to fit with their interests. PhD students often change their interests in the course of their degree, and this strongly counts in favor of choosing a program that is strong overall, not just strong in the student’s area of interest.

## How economists influence policy

Economists rarely influence policy as advisors for people who haven’t made up their minds and want advice. Instead, people who favor a certain position generally seek policy advisors who they will expect will provide arguments favoring their position. So economists, and other policy advisors, often have influence mainly by providing ammunition for advocates of the views they support. There is more room for influence if you provide policy recommendations that are orthogonal to popular disputes.

## What kinds of economic insights are most valuable for doing good?

There is a tendency for people interested in doing good to overemphasize questions about values relative to causal questions about how the social world works. Part of the problem is that people assume that they understand how the social world works, but they do not. A firm grasp of basic economics concepts and theory, developed through years of practice, is very valuable for understanding how the social world works. However, there are strongly diminishing returns to learning much more advanced economics.

## How well do research incentives in economics line up with research that would do the most good?

A great deal of economics is comparing the welfare consequences of different policies, and this research is highly aligned with questions that effective altruists are concerned about. An important difference is that economics tends not to emphasize the methods and political feasibility of enacting different policies as much as effective altruists would like.

For effective altruism, a qualitative, broad understanding of how the world works is very valuable, and there are generally diminishing returns to understanding a topic in greater and greater depth. This conflicts with research incentives in economics, which favor making impressive, in-depth progress on hard questions that many other people work on.

People who feel that economics research incentives do not align with trying to do research that is optimized for positive impact may want to spend 7 to 11 years doing what it takes to get tenure, and then work on whatever it is they want to work on. One can also make substantial contributions outside of one’s academic work.

Research in academia tends to clump onto fashionable topics in a given area, and the incentives favor publishing in these areas. Fashionable areas tend to be more important than average, but marginal contributions yield less progress in areas where a lot of work has already been done. Work on important topics in between clumps can yield great progress for those who can afford to ignore fashion.

# **Places to look for more information**

For information about jobs in economics: look at *Jobs for Economists*.

For information about jobs at think tanks: go to think tank websites and look at the qualifications of people who work at think tanks.

# **Questions discussed in our meeting**

We sent the following questions to Robin Hanson before our meeting to give him a sense of what we were interested in learning. We discussed a subset of them.

	

* Broad questions we want to answer:

  * Who is a good fit for an economics PhD?

  * How valuable is doing an economics PhD for someone trying to maximize the impact of their career? (supposing good fit)

* Who is a good fit for an economics PhD?

  * Is there a level where you’d say "If you can’t get into a PhD program at least X good, you probably shouldn’t go for a PhD in economics"?	

  * Who can actually get admitted to good economics programs?

  * What are good indicators of fit?

  * What are good indicators of bad fit?

  * Who should do a master’s before an economics PhD?

  * Are there other PhDs that someone potentially interested in economics should also consider? How does getting a PhD in economics compare to getting one in math/statistics/comp sci/physics for example?	

* Questions about picking an economics PhD program:

  * What else is important beyond the "tier" program - advisor, topic, other things about the school or department?	

  * What are the most credible rankings of economics departments?

* Questions about the PhD program:

  * How useful is the training and skills building itself? Is most of the value in pure credentials?

  * How good is it for networking?

  * How many hours/how much work do you need to put into an Economics PhD? Is there much opportunity to work on other projects? What kinds of other projects would it be most valuable to spend your time on? 

  * How important is the research topic you choose? How should you choose a research topic, and what should you consider when doing so?

  * How do all of the above vary depending on what tier program you're in?

* Questions about career progression for economics PhDs:

  * Questions about becoming an economics professor:		

    * How hard is it to get a tenure-track job?

      * Do postdocs play a big role in economics?

      * What portion of new PhDs applying for tenure track jobs get tenure track jobs?

    * How hard is it to get tenure?	

      * What portion of people applying for academic jobs get tenure?

      * What portion of people completing economics PhDs get tenure?

  * Non-academic options with economics PhDs

    * Apart from becoming economics professors, what else do econ PhDs do? What portion do these other things?		

    * If you don’t want to be an economics professor, when, if ever, would it make sense to get an economics PhD?

    * Are there special reasons for people interested in effective altruism to get economics PhDs?

* Questions about the value of economics research:		

  * In the history of the discipline, what are some of the main examples where economic research has made substantial contributions to society?

  * In the last couple of decades, what are some of the main examples where economic research has made substantial contributions to society?
]]></content:encoded><dsq:thread_identifier>ā</dsq:thread_identifier><wp:post_date_gmt>2013-10-04 18:45:38</wp:post_date_gmt><wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status></item></channel></rss>
